<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" 
  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" >
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
        Charles Dickens - Brief Bio 
        </title>
        <author>
          <persName>Arunasva Bhuyan</persName>
          <persName>Cameron Cadogan</persName>
          <persName>Oksana Moroko</persName>
          <persName>Sahil Thorul</persName>
          <persName>Talya Vuruskaner</persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab></ab>  
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="Article" source="Oxford Dictionary of National Biography">
          <title>
            Dickens, Charles John Huffam (1812–1870), novelist
          </title>
          <author>
            Michael Slater
          </author>
          <date>2014, September 25</date>
          <note>
            https://www-oxforddnb-com.proxy.bib.uottawa.ca/view/10.1093/ref:odnb/9780198614128.001.0001/odnb-9780198614128-e-7599
          </note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <p> Charles Dickens - Brief Biography</p>
    </front>
    <body>
      
      <p>
        <persName>Charles Dickens</persName> (Charles John Huffam Dickens) was born in 
        <placeName>13 Mile End Terrace, Portsea, Portsmouth</placeName>, on <date>February 7, 1812</date>. 
        Charles was the second oldest of eight children, who were born to their father, 
        <persName>John Dickens</persName> (<date>1786-1851</date>) 
        and their mother, <persName>Elizabeth Dickens</persName> (<date>1789-1863</date>). 
        Charles Dickens' father was a clerk in the Navy Pay office, 
        which allowed his family to have a financially comfortable life.
        The Dickens family spent nine years living on the coastal regions of Kent, a county in southeast England.
      </p>
      
      <p> 
        Unfortunately, life would drastically change for the young <persName>Charles Dickens</persName>. 
        His father was financially irresponsible and pilled up tremendous debts throughout his life. 
        His father's financial situation continued to deteriorate. 
        On <date>February 20th, 1824</date> (when Charles Dickens was 12), 
        <persName>Dickens’ father</persName> was arrested and was sent to  <placeName>Marshalsea debtors' prison</placeName>. 
        Soon enough, Dickens' father was joined by his wife and their younger children. Despite being an avid reader 
        and a promising pupil, Dickens could no longer stay in school. Dickens was forced to
        work with other child laborers. It was a hellish job that involved pasting labels on blacking bottles for 6s a week 
        in a blacking warehouse. </p>
      
      <p>
        These experiences greatly traumatized Charles Dickens. His firsthand experience made him an influential 
        voice for the working class. He actively strived to raise the public's awareness in the fight against 
        poverty, deprivation of education and child labour. 
        In his autobiography, he wrote: 
      </p>

      <quote>
         No words can express the secret agony of my soul as I sunk into this companionship 
        [of ‘common men and boys’] … and felt my early hopes of growing up to be a learned and distinguished man,
        crushed in my breast. The deep remembrance of the sense I had of being utterly neglected and hopeless; 
        of the shame I felt in my position; of the misery it was to my young heart to believe that, day by day, 
        what I had learned, and thought, and delighted in, and raised my fancy and my emulation up by, 
        was passing away from me, never to be brought back any more; cannot be written.
      </quote>  
      <bibl>
        <title>
          The Life of Charles Dickens
        </title>
        <author>
          <persName>John Forster</persName>
        </author>
        <date>1872</date>
      </bibl>
      
      <p>
        The juxtaposition of between economic classes in 
        A Christmas Carol is a direct reflection of Dickens’ experience with poverty as a child working at a workhouse.    
      </p>
      
      <p>
        After his father was released from prison, Dickens returned to school and eventually became
        a law clerk. He went on to serve as a reporter in the courts. Eventually, he worked as 
        as a parliamentary and newspaper reporter.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        In <date>1833</date>, Dickens began his career as novelist. He began publishing short, 
        continous stories periodically. He continued publishing novels to eventually take his place as one of the most popular 
        English novelists of his time. At age 25, Dickens completed his first novel, The Pickwick Papers, 
        which met with great success. He become one of England's most famed and cherised novelist from masterpieces
        such as Great Expectations, A Tale of Two Cities, and later A Christmas Carol. 
      </p>
      
      <p>
        In <date>April of 1836</date>, he married Catherine Hogarth. Together, they had 10 children. 
        Despite, a happy start to their marriage, they eventually divorced in <date>June of 1858</date>. 
        Charles Dickens died at his house on <date>June 9, 1870</date> from a stroke. 
      </p>    
        
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <bibl>
          Slater, Michael. "Dickens, Charles John Huffam (1812–1870), novelist."
          Oxford Dictionary of National Biography. September 25, 2014. Oxford University Press. 
          https://www-oxforddnb-com.proxy.bib.uottawa.ca/view/10.1093/ref:odnb/9780198614128.001.0001/odnb-9780198614128-e-7599
        </bibl>
      </div>
      
      
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
