<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" 
    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" >
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                    Charles Dickens - Brief Bio 
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <ab></ab>  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <p> Charles Dickens - Brief Biography</p>
        </front>
        <body>
            
        <p> Charles Dickens was born on February 7, 1812, and spent the first nine years of his life living in the coastal regions of Kent, 
            a county in southeast England after which point the family moved to London. A few years later, Dickens’ father was arrested and 
            was sent to debtor’s prison for being financially irresponsible and piling up tremendous debts throughout his life. Dickens' mother 
            moved seven of their children into prison with their father and Dickens was arranged to work with other child labourers. It was a 
            hellish job that involved pasting labels on bottles in a blacking warehouse. </p>
         <p>The juxtaposition of the classes in A Christmas Carol is a direct reflection of Dickens’ experience with poverty as a child working 
            at a workhouse in the Victorian England after Industrialization. and Dickens’ transition to a better life upon escaping the precariousness 
            of his childhood. During the months apart that Dickens spent away from his family working alongside other child labourers, he was extremely
            miserable and considered himself too good for it. </p>
          <p>After his father was released from prison, Dickens returned to school and eventually became
            a law clerk. He went on to serve as a court reporter before taking his place as one of the most popular English novelists of his time.
            At age 25, Dickens completed his first novel, The Pickwick Papers, which met with great success. The masterpieces that Dickens produced such as 
            Great Expectations, A Tale of Two Cities, and later A Christmas Carol granted him the status of an English novel celebrity.
         </p>
         <p>Charles Dickens embodies the character of Scrooge, both before an after the transformation. Dickens empathises with the poor, yet
            struggles to let go of his childhood traumas. These traumas made him resentful towards Christmas traditions, as he does not care to indulge 
            his family. Although he was haunted by the thought of repeating his father’s mistakes with financial responsibilities, he is still as cold 
            and uncaring towards his family as his own father once was to him. 
        </p>    
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div><bibl>
                <lb/> 
            </bibl></div>
            

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
