<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Historical Context of <title level="m">A Christmas Carol</title></title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <ab>Encoding<ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">CC-BY=4.0</ref></ab>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>A Christmas Carol was written in 1843, during a time of the declining popularity of the old Christmas traditions. By the early 19th C, 
                there was little left of the old celebration as Puritan influence took over the pagan traditions of the past.The tradition began in A.D.
                601, when Pope Gregory instructed his missionary, St. Augustin of Canterbury, to convert the Anglo Saxons and to transform their local 
                winter feast into a Christian festival. This conversion repurposed of the original pagan customs of Roman Saturnalia, Yule 
                (the Saxon feast for the return of the sun in honour of god Thor), and of the Druid holiday
            </p>
            <p>
                      
            <p> When Charles Dickens was struggling as a serial author for a newspape, he wrote A 
                Christmas Carol with the intention of drawing his readers' attention to the plight of England's poor. Social criticism is a recurring theme 
                in Dickens' work. He uses his novels and his characters to give a voice to those who lack a platform, thus establishing a link between politics 
                and literature. He creates a fictional world that mirrors the truths of the real word to attack the defects of existing institutions. 
                Therefore, Charles Dickens’s novels played a tremendous role in the implementation of policies that changed the lives of the poor. Dickens’s 
                active involvement to promote social reforms raised public awareness in the fight against poverty, deprivation of education, and child labour. 
                In the novel, Dickens combines a slightly indirect description of the hardships faced by the poor with a heart-rending, sentimental celebration 
                of the Christmas season. Ebenezer Scrooge is an apathetic penny-pinching, calloused character, who opens his heart after being confronted by three spirits. He remains one of Dickens’ most widely recognized and popular characters.  
                A major theme in A Christmas Carol comes from depicting the juxtaposition of the different socio-economic classes. With this stark contrast in the embodiment of the ghost that haunts the unfeeling Scrooge, Dickens shows the fragility and elusiveness between the poor and the rich. 
            </p>
            </p>
            <p> In many ways, the Christmas traditions as we know it now were initially popularized by A Christmas Carol.In its current manifestation, 
                Christmas is based on the idea of giving, of receiving, of looking out for the less fortunate, and of feasting with friends and family.
                The symbolism of transformation that Dickens embraces in his novel echoes the process of how Christmas became a traditional holiday in 
                England. In fact, many credit this book for reviving the celebration of Christmas in much of the English-speaking world. 
            </p>
            <p>Charles Dickens plays with the theme of transformation A Christmas Carol as a way of embodying and reflecting upon those societal changes
                shows his dismay at the extreme poverty faced by the working poor living in precarious conditions and struggling to survive. 
                The story of A Christmas Carol can be seen as embodying the harsh realities of the Victorian Britain during the 
                shift to industiralization while embracing the idea of possibility for a change through the spirit of tradition.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            
            <div type="editorial"></div>
            
            <div><bibl>Works Cited<lb/><author>Bronte, Charoltte</author>.<title level="m"> Jane Eyre</title>.<pubPlace> New York:</pubPlace><publisher> Oxford University Press</publisher>,<date> 2008</date>.  print. </bibl></div>
            <div><bibl><lb/><author> Marcus, Sharon.</author><title> Between Women : Friendship, Desire, and Marriage in Victorian England.</title><pubPlace>  Princeton:</pubPlace><publisher> Princeton UP,</publisher><date> 2007.</date> Print.</bibl></div>
            <div> <bibl><lb/><lb/><author> Morgan, Simon.</author><title> A Victorian Woman's Place : Public Culture in the Nineteenth Century.</title><pubPlace>  London: New York :</pubPlace><publisher> Tauris Academic Studies,</publisher><date> 2007.</date> Print.</bibl></div>
            
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
